<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A form of prayer and thanksgiving for the safe delivery of the Queen and happy birth of the young Prince to be used ... in all churches and chappels ...</title>
            <author>Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4168</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35992</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15585926</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15585926</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103963</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33048)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103963)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1184:84)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A form of prayer and thanksgiving for the safe delivery of the Queen and happy birth of the young Prince to be used ... in all churches and chappels ...</title>
                  <author>Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Charles Bill, Henry Hills, and Thomas Newcomb ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"By His Majesties special command."</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  of Modena, Queen, consort of James II, King of England, 1658-1718.</term>
               <term>James, --  Prince of Wales, 1688-1766.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Prayer-books and devotions.</term>
               <term>Prayers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103963:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <p>A FORM OF PRAYER WITH THANKSGIVING FOR THE Safe Delivery of the QUEEN, And happy BIRTH of the Young Prince.</p>
            <p>TO BE Uſed on <hi>Sunday</hi> next, being the Seventeeth Day of this Inſtant <hi>June,</hi> in all Churches and Chappels, within the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>weſtminſter,</hi> and Ten Miles diſtance; And upon the Firſt Day of <hi>July</hi> next, in all other Places throughout this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By His Majeſties ſpecial Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Charles Bill, Henry Hills,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Newcomb,</hi> Printers to the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty. 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prayer_service">
            <pb facs="tcp:103963:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <head>A FORM of PRAYER WITH THANKSGIVING For the ſafe Delivery of the QUEEN, and happy Birth of the Young PRINCE. To be Uſed on <hi>Sunday</hi> next, being the 17th Day of this inſtant <hi>June,</hi> in all Churches and Chappels within the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>VVeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and Ten Miles diſtance; and upon the Firſt Day of <hi>July</hi> next, in all other Places throughout this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>VVales,</hi> and Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ This Service ſhall be the ſame with the uſual Office for the Days above named, except where it is hereafter otherwiſe appointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <stage>¶ At the beginning of Morning Prayer the Miniſter ſhall read theſe Sentences following.</stage>
            <q>
               <p>OFfer unto the Lord Thankſgiving:<note place="margin">Pſal. l. 14.</note> and pay thy Vows unto the moſt High.</p>
               <p>An Offering of a free heart will I give thee:<note place="margin">Pſal. liv. 6.</note> and praiſe thy Name, O Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:103963:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
¶ In the place of <hi>[Venite exultemus]</hi> ſhall be uſed this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Hymn.</stage>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Give thanks unto the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. cv. ver. 1.</note> and call upon his Name: tell the people what things he hath done.</p>
               <p rend="roman">O let your ſongs be of him,<note place="margin">2.</note> 
                  <hi>and praiſe him: let your talking be of all his wondrous works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Give the Lord the honour due unto his Name:<note place="margin">xxlx. 2.</note> worſhip the Lord with holy worſhip.</p>
               <p rend="roman">One generation ſhall praiſe thy works unto another:<note place="margin">cxlv. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>and declare thy power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For thou,<note place="margin">xcii. 4.</note> Lord, haſt made me glad through thy works: I will rejoyce in giving praiſe, for the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of thy hands.</p>
               <p rend="roman">I will ſing of the Lord becauſe he hath dealt ſo lovingly with me:<note place="margin">xili. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>yea, I will praiſe the Name of the Lord moſt High.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord is my ſtrength:<note place="margin">xxviii. 9.</note> he is the wholſome defence of his Anointed.</p>
               <p rend="roman">Great proſperity giveth he unto his King:<note place="margin">xviii. 51.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſheweth loving kindneſs to David his Anointed, and to his ſeed for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O that men would therefore praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs:<note place="margin">cvii. 21.</note> and declare the wonders he doth for the children of men.</p>
               <p rend="roman">That they would offer unto him the ſacrifice of thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving:<note place="margin">22.</note> 
                  <hi>and tell out his works with gladneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That they would eralt him alſo in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the People:<note place="margin">32.</note> and praiſe him in the ſeat of the Elders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p rend="roman">For his merciful kindneſs is ever more and more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us:<note place="margin">cxvii. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>and the truth of the Lord endureth for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Glory be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p rend="roman">As it was in the beginning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:103963:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
¶ Proper Pſalms 72.89.</stage>
            <stage>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ Proper Leſſons</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſaiah 12.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>St. Matth. 22.</hi> from v. 15. to the end.</item>
               </list>
            </stage>
            <stage>¶ To be added in the Verſicles after the Creed.<lb/>
               <l>O Lord, ſave the King.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let his ſeed be mighty upon earth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let him evermore rejoyce in thy ſtrength.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And be exceeding glad in thy ſalvation.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O Lord, ſave the Queen.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And make her as a fruitful Vine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Endue thy Miniſters with righteouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </stage>
            <stage>¶ The firſt Collect inſtead of that for the day.</stage>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Almighty and everlaſting Lord God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, who madeſt the World and all that is therein, and giveſt to all men life and breath and all things; We devoutly offer our moſt hearty thanks to thy Divine Majeſty, that thou haſt given our Dread Sovereign his hearts deſire, and haſt not denied us the requeſt of our lips, in bleſſing him and our Gracious Queen with a Son, and all his Subjects with a Prince: Stabliſly the thing; O God, that thou haſt wrought among us. Grant the Princely Infant health, ſtrength, and long life, that he may grow up to live in thy fear, and to thy glory, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in all virtues becoming his high Birth, and the Royal Dignity to which thou haſt ordained him. O prepare thy loving mercy and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that they may ever preſerve him, for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of thy Name, and the eſtabliſhment of the pence, ſecurity and happineſs of theſe Nations from generation to generation, and this we beg
<pb facs="tcp:103963:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake our only Mediatour and Redeemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <stage>¶ At the end of the Litany, immediately after <hi>[We humbly beſeech thee]</hi> this following Prayer is to be uſed.</stage>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſt powerful and glorious God, who art wonderful in all the myſterious acts of thy Providence, and adorable in the various diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions of thy juſtice and mercy to the children of men; We meekly humble our ſelves, and fall low before the footſtool of thy grace, rendring thee all worſhip and thanks, that, although for our manifold ſins moſt juſtly provoking thee, thou in thy wrath haſt heretofore taken from us ſo many of the Royal Progeny, yet in the midſt of judgment thou haſt remembred mercy, and according to thy continual goodneſs haſt revived our hopes, and begun to repair our former loſſes, by renewing fruitfulneſs to the Queen, and giving birth to a Royal Prince. We beſeech thee, O Lord, give the King and all his People, ſuch a due ſenſe of this thy mercy, that our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout and thankful acceptance, and right uſe of it, may divert thy judgments for the future, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thee to beſtow more ſuch publick bleſſings upon us. So we who are thy people will reioyce evermore, in every thing giving thanks unto thee, through our only Mediatour and Advocate Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:103963:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->
¶ In the Communion-Service next after the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the firſt Collect ſhall be the ſame as in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prayer, [<hi>O Almighty and Everlaſting Lord God of heaven and earth, &amp;c.</hi>]</stage>
            <stage>¶ Then ſhall follow one of the two Collects for the King.
<list>
                  <item>¶ The Epiſtle, Coloſ. III. from verſ. 12. to v. 18.</item>
                  <item>¶ The Goſpel, S. Luke I. from verſ. 57. to v. 67.</item>
               </list>
            </stage>
            <stage>¶ After the Prayer for the Church Militant, ſhall follow this Prayer.</stage>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord our Governour, whoſe Name is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in all the World, and who art king for ever and ever: We praiſe and bleſs thy Divine Goodneſs, for all the marvellous Protections, and ſignal Favours, thou haſt vouchſafed thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant our Gracious King <hi>JAMES:</hi> particularly that after thou hadſt preſerved him from the dangers of War, from the rage of the Sea, and from the madneſs of the People, thou didſt in thy due time bring him to great honour, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tling him on the Throne of his Anceſtors, and haſt now enlarged thy Bleſſings towards him, by this happy increaſe of the Royal Iſſue: We moſt humbly beſeech Thee, to continue and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply theſe thy mercies to Him and Vs: That thou would'ſt give him Sons to grow up as the young plants, and that his daughters may be as the poliſh'd Corners of the Temple. Bleſs, O Lord, the whole Royal Family, with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the Heavens above, with the bleſſings of the Deep beneath, with the bleſſings of the Breaſts and of the Womb: That when the
<pb facs="tcp:103963:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->King's days ſhall be fulfilled, and he ſhall ſleep with his Fathers in Peace and Glory, his Seed may be ſet up after him, and his Houſe and Kingdom may be eſtabliſh'd for ever before Thee. Grant this, O Lord, for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake our only Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
